Tucson Council for Civic Unity records, 1948-1966
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Tucson Council for Civic Unity records, 1948-1966
MS 317
Tucson Council for Civic Unity
This collection contains Board of Director and general membership files, meeting minutes, correspondence, financial papers, programs, newspaper clippings and subject files. Subject files include pamphlets, flyers and other formats on a variety of Tucson agencies and civil rights activities; and Council's activities in the Arizona state legislative process concerning civil rights issues of the day: school desegregation, equal employment opportunities, human relations, public accommodations; and related information and publications on other state organizations and federal issues. Also includes files, 1948-1960, on the early years of Arizona Council for Civic Unity.
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Tucson Council for Civic Unity (TCCU) was dedicated "to foster and promote better understanding and relations among people of various racial, religious, social and national backgrounds in Arizona and to promote better conditions among all groups with respect to education, housing, employment, recreation, health and other community problems." It was affiliated with the Arizona Council for Civic Unity (ACCU: incorporated December 21, 1948). The Greater Phoenix Council for Civic Unity was another local agency for the ACCU.
ACCU's founder was Dr. Fred G. Holmes, whose interest in initiating this agency was triggered by President Truman's Commission on Civil Rights' report of 1946, To Secure these Rights. During 1946-1947, Holmes worked with Louis Wirth and Louis E. Hosch of the American Council for Race Relations in Chicago on planning the Arizona Council for Civic Unity. Many well-known Tucsonans were involved with TCCU over the years, including Morris and Stewart Udall, Mr. and Mrs. Morgan Maxwell, Maria Urquides, Rabbi Bilgray, Dorothy Barber, Laura Banks, Thomas Bahti, Harry Gin and Sam Goddard.
The Council contributed to several achievements including the desegregation of Tucson public schools, 1948-1951, and repeal of school segregation laws in Arizona; the passage of the Equal Employment Opportunity bill, 1955; the creation of the Human Relations Commission, 1955; and in many daily local battles against racial and religious discrimination. TCCU's longest struggle was for the passage of the Public Accommodations legislation in the Arizona State Legislature. The effort lasted from 1949-1965, when the Civil Rights bill was finally enacted.
Organization
This collection is organized into two subgroups:
Subgroup I: Tucson Council for Civic Unity, 1948-1966
Subgroup II: Arizona Council for Civic Unity, 1948-1960
Scope and Content Note
The first subgroup, the Tucson Council for Civic Unity records, pertains to the council's activities in Tucson and in the state legislature to achieve its mission. Historical information includes the constitution and by-laws, and background information about TCCU. Board of directors lists, 1948-1965, meeting minutes from 1951-1965, and treasurers' reports from 1951-1962 are included. Correspondence on general matters is divided into two folders. Membership files are divided into membership lists and membership meeting minutes, both arranged chronologically from 1948-1965. Membership lists from 1961, 1962 and 1964 are missing. There is also a file of internal memos, meeting notices and a few newsletters sent to members. Various programs, conferences and committees sponsored or cosponsored by TCCU, 1950-1964 are arranged in folder. A series of subject files covers Tucson organizations and civil rights activities during 1949-1964; Arizona civil rights legislative activities from 1948-1965; regional and national organizations; and supplemental files of newspaper clippings from 1948-1965, and including related publications in comic book formats of civil rights issues, one featuring Martin Luther King.
The second subgroup of records involves the Arizona Council for Civic Unity, 1947-1960. These few files are incomplete. Included are Board of Directors lists, 1948-1957 [lacking 1950-1953 and 1955]; the meeting minutes from 1948-1958 [these too are incomplete]; Financial records, 1950-1952, are mostly tax information. Both incoming and outgoing correspondence is filed. The bulk of this correspondence is with Louis Wirth and Louis Hosch of the American Council on Race Relations and Fred Holmes regarding the early development of ACCU; and between Fred Holmes and Executive Secretary Rosamond Spicer. A few newsletters from 1948-1958 are also present here. A supplemental group of files, containing a historical file, 1947-1949; a file on Greater Phoenix Council for Civic Unity, and a miscellaneous file are included as well.
Spicer, Edward Holland, 1906-; Spicer, Rosamond B.; Udall, Stewart L.; Wirth, Louis, 1897-1952.; Holmes, Fred G.; Tucson Council for Civic Unity -- Archives.; Arizona Council for Civic Unity -- Correspondence.; Greater Phoenix Council for Civic Unity -- Correspondence.; American Council on Race Relations -- Correspondence.; Citizens' associations -- Arizona.; Civil rights -- Arizona.; School integration -- Arizona.; Records.; Tucson (Ariz.) -- History -- 20th century.
Separated Material
Approximately 2 linear feet of records was not retained, mainly duplicates, bank statements, ledgers, bills and receipts.
Container List
- Subgroup 1: Tucson Council for Civic Unity, 1948-1966
  - Series 1: Historical Information, 1948-1963
    - Historical information. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Series 2: Officers, 1948-1965
    - Board of Directors' lists. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors' meeting minutes. (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Treasurers' Reports, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Series 3: Correspondence, 1948-1966
    - Incoming (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
    - Outgoing (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Outgoing (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Series 4: Membership, 1948-1965
    - Membership lists (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Meeting minutes (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Internal memos, notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Series 5: Programs, 1950-1964
    - Committee on Intercultural Education, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Conference on Human Relations, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Other programs sponsored by TCCU. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Series 6: Subject files, 1947-1965
    - Civil Rights Congress of Tucson, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies (later named Tucson Community Council), 1950-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - IMPACT, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Operation Good Neighbor, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Other organizations, 1947-1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Tucson Commission on Human Relations, 1955-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - University of Arizona segregation information, 1948-1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - School Desegregation, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - State Commission on Human Relations, 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Public Accommodations, 1954-1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re: public accommodations, 1954-1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Equal Employment Opportunities, 1952-1958 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Civil Rights (final bill), 1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Various other state legislative actions, 1950-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous state legislative information, 1949-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - American Council on Race Relations, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - California Federation for Civic Unity, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Civil rights reports from various US cities, 1948-1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Colorado Civic Unity, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Fair Employment Practices Commission, 1949-ca.1950's (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Housing, 1949-1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - National Association of Intergroup Relations Officials, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Native Americans information, ca.1950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - United World Federalists, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Urban Renewal, ca.1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Series 7: Supplemental materials, 1948-1965
    - TCCU: miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Printed matter: 3 booklets on civil rights, including Martin Luther King: the Montgomery story (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Subgroup 2: Arizona Council for Civic Unity, 1948-1960
  - Series 1: ACCU, Boards of Directors, 1948-1957
    - Board of Directors lists (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Series 2: ACCU meeting minutes, 1948-1958
    - Meeting minutes (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Series 3: ACCU financial records, 1950-1952
    - Financial records (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Series 4: ACCU correspondence, 1947-1958
    - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - American Council on Race Relations, 1947-1949 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Fred Holmes, 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Series 5: ACCU supplemental, 1947-1960
    - Historical file, 1947-1949 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1955 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Greater Phoenix Council for Civic Unity, 1948-1960 (Box 6, Folder 9)